<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title></title>
        <link>https://pangolune.com</link>
        <description></description>
        <generator>Zola</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <atom:link href="https://pangolune.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>Chapter 4: Chickpea</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://pangolune.com/4/</link>
            <guid>https://pangolune.com/4/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Chickpea and Pango had been on the ship for two days. Chickpea’s wing had not improved. The bone set wrong and every sway of the ship caused it to stab her somewhere inside her wing. She held still and breathed long measured breaths to reduce movement to the minimum. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;4&#x2F;1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far the ferrets that smuggled them on the ship had not mistreated her or Pango. They were kind, even. Once aboard, Diane let them out of the crate into Nadelle’s cabin. Nadelle was the granddaughter of some customer who Diane had seduced into coming back with her to Springville. Pango reminded Chickpea more than once that his name was Eddard. The third time she only pretended to have forgotten, to annoy him. There was a plan to marry Nadelle to Diane’s grandson, or something like that, but Chickpea had a broken wing to focus on and maintained only a limited awareness of her surroundings and company.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Northenden Chickpea ate breakfast in the early AM, because she had to. As soon as the sun rays poked through the maple leaves she hopped out of her nest and started her warmup exercises, high kicks and winding her wings in large circles. She woke up all at once. There was no easing into it for her. Her nest in the mountain forest was a 15 minute flight from breakfast, in town. If she flapped desperately, she could cover the distance in only 10 minutes. On-time arrival for breakfast was imperative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the party disappeared her parents and imprisoned her brother, Chickpea blazed her own trail. In her first days alone, before she understood the role of birds in Northenden, she knocked on the door of James Everett Public Orphanage by biting the door knocker in her beak, flying back, and letting it fall on the door. When a red coated fox answered the door, she asked for room and board and the general help a young and guardianless birdling might expect from a minimally empathetic society. The fox glanced down and then snapped back up and pretended not to have seen Chickpea. His act didn’t convince her. Even at that time, when she was more forgiving in her reads of others, she found it implausible that someone would miss a bright blue songbird on a sunny day only inches from themselves, even if the glance was short. This fox was playing her. She responded with the indignant stubbornness of a child with disappointed expectations. For days she abused the door’s knocker, banging it without rhythm, at unpredictable intervals, in her best attempt to torment whoever had denied her what she felt owed. They never answered, and they removed the knocker. Northenden had one orphanage, so with all one of her options exhausted, Chickpea self-sustained in her own way. Her own way consisted mostly of stealing food out of folk’s hands at the town market and booking it straight upward as fast as she could fly with the loot, plus some more elaborate schemes here and there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What she could steal from the market—bites of cinnamon bread or salted pretzels on good days—it was nothing compared to her breakfast arrangement. Her breakfast arrived at #3 Claw Street at a specific time every morning, just a few minutes after dawn. An elderly fox with both feet in the grave, sort of sitting at the grave’s edge with both feet in and just testing the water, lived alone at #3 Claw Street. As far as Chickpea could tell, she did nothing at all. She never left the house and no one ever came to visit. Chickpea flew over that street every day on the way to the market, and over time acquainted herself with the tops of the heads of at least one resident from every home except #3. Curious, she flew down to a window and peered inside and found an old fox splayed out on a reclining chair, eyes open, staring at the ceiling. Her chest moved, so she was still breathing. Somehow this fox was getting food without leaving her home. Chickpea staked the place out, which the house readily accommodated because the unrepaired holes in the roof were big enough for her to infiltrate the attic. Just after dawn, two red coats delivered a fresh meal in a box. The aroma rose up to Chickpea, who was leaning over and watching from the roof. She smelled soy sauce, peanut butter, roast bok choy, and some spice she didn’t recognize. And it just sat there in front of the door. Not stupid, Chickpea waited to see when the old fox would fetch the meal each morning. For a week she timed it—over a lifetime of in-and-out food theft, Chickpea honed a metronome-caliber ability to count on exact seconds—and after seven days felt she had a safe plan. If she arrived prior to the box’s delivery and dove for it the moment the red coats left, she had five minutes to open the box, carry some of each entree to the attic, and close the box again. The stolen food was hardly noticeable to a fox, but it was heavy eating for a songbird. Eating premium party food in the privacy of that attic was the grandest material pleasure Chickpea had ever lucked into.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea was thinking about that bok choy now, and how she’d probably never eat it again. In the adjacent room, Diane and Eddard’s, the whole crew sans Chickpea—Pango had started referring to the ferrets inclusively as part of “the crew”—were playing some card game, and occasionally erupted into yelling and yowling and other tedious sounds in reaction to events in the card game. Chickpea couldn’t cover her ears because of the broken wing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea’s habitual spaced-out way of thinking and passing mental time was to scheme. She liked to fly around Northenden and survey the activity and leisurely ponder how she could leverage her observations to some end. But now she wasn’t in Northenden and likely never would be again, was heading toward somewhere she’d never been before where she didn’t know the threats or have any sense of what was reasonable to pull off, and when she got there, she would have to waddle, vulnerable on the ground around the feet of larger animals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango returned to the room and gave Chickpea a toy earlier in the day. He said it was Eddard’s and that it was “really cool”. Chickpea hadn’t inspected it since he set it down right beside her in reach of her good wing. She couldn’t help but look down on Pango’s eagerness to attach to these ferrets. They met only days ago but he’d already started acting like they were his parents. It nauseated her to see Pango make himself at home and fawn over Eddard’s stories of whatever a ferret has to suffer in their life, which is probably very little. There’s not much to do in a room alone without being able to move, though. Dire boredom drove her to pick up Eddard’s toy and give it a once over.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;4&#x2F;2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toy was a little pillar, above which was a spinning marble. The marble was elevated an inch over the pillar by something thin and hard to see. Chickpea held it upside down and squinted at the gap between the marble and the top of the pillar and saw…nothing. There was nothing between the marble and the surface beneath it. It levitated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A panel with a visible outline slid off. Wrinkled pink flesh filled the inside of the toy. Lights and small metal contacts she could press like buttons lined the sides, 8 on each side. When Chickpea pressed one of the buttons, the marble launched from its levitating position to the left, and rolled across the room and clanked against the water pail.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiosity compelled her to hobble across the room, leaning on the crates to stabilize herself against the sways of the ship. She settled into an economical spot next to the water pail and picked up the fallen marble.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Chickpea brought the marble close to the pillar on the toy, close but not touching, it snapped back into its levitating place. She held the marble there with her unbroken wing and tested pressing in each button with her beak. Pressing each contact pushed the marble in a different direction. Somehow they were calibrated to keep the marble floating in place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was deep in analysis when Pango and Nadelle returned from a long day of whatever they had been loudly doing over there in the other room. With a sharp metal scrap she’d found in one of the crates, Chickpea had scratched a chart into the wall. It had a column for each of the toy’s metal contacts and another column for observations. She had her own language of symbols to write in, which meant nothing to anyone else. In the rows she wrote the state of each button (pressed or unpressed) and which direction the combination propelled the marble.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Pango fell asleep, Nadelle rolled over in her hammock and whispered to Chickpea. “Hey lil bird. I need your help with something.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea did not reply. She had to finish scratching in the row of data before she forgot the states of each button.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;4&#x2F;3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Lil bird. I got a job for you when we get to Springville. I’ll make it worth your time.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea pointed to the toy. “I’m testing this thing.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Uh. Ok. Do you want to hear about the job?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea paused her scribbling to roll her eyes, which Nadelle couldn’t see because she was facing the wall. How had Nadelle not noticed the broken wing in two days? How had that not come up between her and Pango when they were playing cards all day? “Isn’t your granddad marrying you off down there?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s sort of what this is about.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let’s talk later Nadelle, I’m focused.” She couldn’t fly, so she couldn’t help. She didn’t want to have to say that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tomorrow.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Chapter 3: Pango</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://pangolune.com/3/</link>
            <guid>https://pangolune.com/3/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The book “An Enchanted Fruit of Your Own”, authored by a renowned botanist from a university in Chenowth named Nadia Gombo, cost the same amount of gold as a single bird’s passage off of the island of Northenden. According to the catalogue Pango circled it in, the book instructed readers on how to grow enchanted fruits right at home. That was perfect because home is where Pango preferred to remain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he climbed out of the window, he pictured himself picking an enchanted peach off a tree grown in the safety of his room. Whether it was practical to grow a peach tree inside his house, he didn’t know, but he tried to focus on the possible positive outcomes of his decision now that he had made it and would not turn back. He stayed low as he snuck around the back of the house, so his mother would not see him, and then rushed to meet Chickpea at the market.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango’s calculations were thorough and he believed this risk was necessary. Helping Chickpea run her scam would earn him some influence over the money, with which he could persuade her to order a copy of “An Enchanted Fruit of Your Own” and the materials it required instead of purchasing passage off the island. If Chickpea left on her own, he would still need the gold to buy the book, and there was no way for a bird to legitimately earn gold in Northenden. If he ran this scam with her, Chickpea might stay safe on an island she knew well instead of facing trials only the gods know to reach the southern end of the world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when he arrived at the market, these conclusions fled him and he tried unsuccessfully to recall the logical steps he took to reach them the first time, so he could walk them again. In the place of his resolve, he imagined his mother scolding him, comparing him to his father, and he felt ashamed. She had already lost her husband to idealism, to ambition. How could Pango rob her of her son? He should know better. Did he really think a book anyone could order out of a catalogue would solve a problem for all of Northenden? He should keep his head down and focus on things in his control, which did not include politics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He checked the clocktower every few minutes. Assuming his mother did not stop by his room and ask him a question through the door before she delivered lunch at 12 PM, he had 2 hours and 45 minutes before she realized his room was empty. This could not be allowed to happen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea pecked at his head. “It’s us!”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the crowd in front of them, beside a tall stack of wooden tables, a soldier yelled “80!” over and over again. Pango pushed through the crowd, steering through other chickens so as not to bump any foxes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have area 80. Will you rent a table?” the fox said when he read their papers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No, we don’t have any money,” Pango said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can pay after, for double price.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango wanted to check the clock tower again, and debt to the party did not excite him. But Chickpea said “We’ll take one.” She whispered to Pango that it was essential they look professional while selling fake merchandise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the fox lowered the papers and looked down at his new lendees, Pango felt afraid. He had never been so close to a soldier before. The fox’s spear was three times taller than Pango, as thick as his neck, and capped by a black stone chiseled into a skewed raindrop so it could rupture the skin and invade flesh. He would not dare play fickle, so he let Chickpea’s ill-thought purchase stand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table weighed much more than Pango. And Chickpea was of course too small to help when it came to moving the thing. Even pulling it on a wheeled cart gave him frightening thoughts of his hollow fowl bones cracking and bending in two. He collapsed under the shade of the table when he finally arrived in area 80, and rested until he stopped wheezing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he regained his breath and sat up to check the clock tower, he suffered a grave realization. He checked left and right and did not see it. Wincing, he tilted his head straight up, at the unreadable thin underside of the clock. Area 80 was located directly beneath it. Now he could not check the time, and thanks to Chickpea any attempt to rush home would first be delayed by a grueling trip to return the table.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango took stock of their neighbors. Across the street, an old ferret sold copper sculptures with embedded gemstones. She had a sign that read “Forms by Diane”. To their left and right, chicken families sold harvests of beets and potatoes. Honest products surrounded their booth, and Pango felt he and Chickpea were too obvious among them. At least one soldier paced by at all times, and Pango feared that if one caught on and accused them of running a scam, even these soldier-loathing chickens would look down on them for their dishonesty.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diane gave each child in a group of little foxes a handle to hold up and told them to run. As they did, a puppet expanded into a large snake which appeared to slither along above their heads. It was cute, and innocent, and when Pango looked down at the peach pits he had painted with a golden vein sitting on their table, he wanted to hide his sins. He buried his head in his wings on the table.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re going to scare off customers if you sleep there, Pango.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea was right. Pango left the booth to her and crossed the street for a view of the clocktower. It was 10:10 AM. Less than two hours remained before he had to be home. He looked hopefully at passing foxes, picking out the ones wearing jewelry, and prayed they would stop and talk to Chickpea so she could nab their gold and he could go on home, but five of them passed without even looking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spot he chose to stand for his view of the clock tower was too close to Diane’s booth. Diane had taken a pause in her conversation with a customer and was looking at him. He knew he had to look away. He knew he had to break her eye contact before she decided that his cataleptic reaction betrayed guilt. He thought of prison, and tried to remember what they did with thieves. No, it was not the time to be browsing memories. He had to look away, look away at anything.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her crate. The first thing Pango looked at when he looked away was her merchandise crate, possibly the worst choice. He cringed, but when he smiled at Diane and pretended to look with interest at her sculptures, she resumed her conversation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;He is very handsome, very very handsome,&amp;quot; she was telling her customer, who was also an old ferret, with passion. &amp;quot;He can speak all three tongues, and he invested in the Pale Ox mining company well before they found mithril. Now he owns land outside Springville, with plenty of room for a wife and children. Many children!&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;5.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customer let out a nose-exhale kind of laugh and played with his beard. &amp;quot;That&#x27;s a strong case, but I fear I&#x27;ve spent all of my granddaughter&#x27;s patience for my recommendations. She would rather travel than marry at this age&amp;quot; he said, before shyly mumbling off &amp;quot;I&#x27;m particularly interested in this tree sculpture of yours, maybe you could tell me something about — &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Going to Palestan is travel! I&#x27;m going back tonight.&amp;quot; She put her paw on top of his. &amp;quot;I&#x27;ve got two rooms on the ship. Your granddaughter can take one, and we can share the other.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango decided that was a good time to walk away. He sat down in area 80 behind their table to think while Chickpea hopped around enticing customers. What did they do with fraudsters? He knew about the prisons only what his mother had told him. They handled birds in two ways. For some crimes, a bird was thrown into the cage, a giant network of caves with all of the openings covered in metal grates. This was bad, but not a horror. Most of the birds in the cage were imprisoned for crimes as simple as looking at a soldier without the proper amount of respect. The prisoners were soft, and they were fed. There was no freedom, or sunlight, but because he was presently committing a crime Pango focused on the tolerable aspects. For other crimes a bird was noosed. Pango wracked his brain to recall which of these two punishments the party applied to fraudsters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fox approached their table and Chickpea was talking to him. Pango tuned in because he thought the fox sounded suspiciously young.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Let me make sure I understand, because our product doesn&#x27;t work in all situations. You love this girl? You think you&#x27;re right for her?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, yes.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;But this love is one-sided?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well, I think she knows that I&#x27;m right for her, she&#x27;s just tied up in something right now. We used to hang out all the time but we barely do anymore since she got this boyfriend. No one really likes the guy. I have no idea how he pulled the wool over her eyes, but he&#x27;s got her trapped in something thick. On the rare occasions that we do hang out, all she wants to do is talk about him —”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay —”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“— which is so frustrating because I&#x27;m right there and clearly —&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Okay, I understand. What&#x27;s your name?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Peter.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You have a great name, Peter. My name is Angela,&amp;quot; Chickpea said. &amp;quot;Now listen Peter, you&#x27;re lucky because we do have what you need. Any peach core that&#x27;s gold has some magic, but you have to pay attention to the pattern because that tells you what kind of magic. This one here is the one you need.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;On the day you feel most brave, you&#x27;ll eat this. Then the first person that you confess your love for that day will fall in love with you. But remember: you have to do it the same day that you eat it and it will only work if you are truly in love.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh, I am truly in love. I know it.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Then I wish you and your future wife many happy days.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is how their empty pouch became a pouch full of more gold than either of them had ever seen in their life.  Pango stood up behind Chickpea to see the end of the transaction for himself. The fox slid gold coins into the pouch that Chickpea held open with her beak. The duped fox had not walked away yet, so Pango had to abstain from looking in the pouch and staring at the sparkles from the sunlight reflecting off of the coins, reaching into the pouch and feeling the cold metal shape around his fingers like liquid as he dragged his wing through the coins, and also from running away as fast as possible to bury the coins, so as not to create suspicion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once he got over the shock of owning gold for the first time, Pango wondered why a young fox had so much to spend. A fox Peter’s age could not earn his own gold. He must belong to a family with gratuitous wealth if his parents provided him such an allowance, and only members of the party could become so rich...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango lifted his eyes to look at Peter again. An older fox wearing a red vest with white trim guided Peter away with a hand on his shoulder. They left the gold, but the older fox was looking back, at Pango, straight into his eyes. Coming here was a mistake. Years of hesitation and careful planning blew away in the wind. Was Pango so stupid? Obscurity had been his only shield in this world, and now he had come to the attention of the party.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He knows and he saw me.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;7.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t worry Pango. Foxes can’t tell chickens apart,” Chickpea said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No, he saw me. We have to go home and warn my mother.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If he can really recognize you, and he can’t, going home would just lead him to your mother. Just wait. They’re not going to arrest us here. It’s bad press.” Chickpea said this with half her attention as she nudged the pouch of gold coins off the table and hid it under pine needles on the ground. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He tried to distract himself while he waited for the crowd to leave by watching other booths, but images of soldiers taking his mother intruded on his mind. How Chickpea managed to stay calm and seduce customers under these conditions escaped his understanding, but she at least agreed not to sell to any more foxes. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diane stared at them whenever she wasn’t occupied with a customer or the old ferret she had been flirting with, who stopped by her booth every half hour. Pango overheard that his name was Eddard. After Diane pointed Pango out to Eddard, Eddard began staring at him too sometimes. What were they saying? It frustrated Pango to not know. He wanted to make them explain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large crate behind Diane’s booth drew his attention, and he pretended to be checking out a booth beside hers to get a better look at it. It was far larger than it needed to be to fit her merchandise inside. He knew it wasn’t full in the morning because he had not seen her sell any sculptures. A horizontal divider separated two compartments, and the top compartment had holes in the sides. Air holes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he saw the holes he bolted back to area 80 and hid behind the table. Diane wasn’t here to sell sculptures. She was here to kidnap birds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s going to kidnap us.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The ferret? Would you relax, Pango?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;8.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’d like to. But he would not. It must have been at least half an hour after lunchtime now. His mother would be worried. Though it would be of no help, he wanted to know the time, so he walked out for a view of the clocktower taking care to avoid Diane’s booth. It was 12:40 PM, so his mother had been suffering for 40 minutes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he heard his mother scream.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could she be there? His mother would never venture so far from home as the market.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she screamed again Pango felt his chest tighten and constrict his heart. A tingling sensation emerged in the tips of his fingers, making them stiff and less responsive. He ran through the crowd toward the sound, oblivious to who he was pushing out of the way. Finally he made it to the source, area 80, but he did not see Chickpea at the table. Another scream came from an alley behind the clocktower. He followed the echoes of the scream into the alley.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surreal scene unfolded before him when he rounded the corner. The red vest, Peter’s father, walked ahead of two soldiers. One of the soldiers dragged his mother by a rope they had bound her in. The other soldier, fallen behind by a few meters, jabbed at Chickpea with his spear.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea dove in, beak first, for his eye. The fox made a shrill sound when it became one-eyed, but neither the red vest nor the other soldier turned to check on him. He removed her with his claw and threw her to the ground, breaking her left wing. He tried to jab Chickpea with his spear again and she struggled to dodge by hopping laterally with a lopsided flap.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foxes were carrying away his only family and his only friend. He stood paralyzed by an unsolvable problem. If he tried to fight the foxes, he would die. If he tried to rescue them and run, he could only carry Chickpea, and it wouldn&#x27;t matter anyway because he could not outrun a fox. If he did nothing, he would be alone, guilty, and ashamed. The tightness in his chest progressed, and the tingling sensation from the tips of his fingers crawled up his arms and into his face. A feeling gripped him which must have emerged from deep within his mind, a central primal part which provides the information that precedes thought, because the feeling was not a conscious reaction or process but raw perception, as undeniable as the colors of his vision and the sounds of his hearing, and it was that violence was due. His whole body tensed and he imagined gripping the neck of a soldier and smashing his head into rock repeatedly until the soldier’s only experience was suffering and finally he became inanimate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without thought, with an entirely silent mind, Pango sprinted back to the booth and fetched the pouch of gold coins. When he returned to the alley, the foxes carrying away his mother had already turned a corner out of sight. One victim remained and Pango looked only at his victim. He launched the first swing from behind and achieved impact at the top of a beautiful arc. The fox stumbled, and Pango seized the opportunity to pose for a two armed overhead swing. By the time the fox turned around to see Pango the pouch of coins was almost down upon his head.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;9.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fox was an object now. Wheezing sounds escaped from it between the swings Pango brought down upon its neck. There was no objective, there was no context. Pango was not a chicken or anything else and there was nothing outside of this action. To exist was to raise and lower the weight in his hands upon this pathetic disgusting object on the ground with as much force as possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;10.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments after he sat down to rest on completion of his task he was disturbed by a pecking sensation in his feet which had just begun, or at least just come to his attention. Pango looked down to see a small blue bird emoting and yelling something at him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a narrow tunnel through which Pango could carry only a single thought, he emerged into his usual awareness. He recognized the bird and in a short, rapid transition what became strange was not the bird requesting his attention, but the memories of the moment before that took place in a foreign state of mind. Chickpea increased her volume as he did not respond.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;PANGO!&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He could not help but fixate on how strange the state of mind he just exited was, how unlike any of his other memories it was, and how because it was unlike any other he did not know where to put it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hi, yes I&#x27;m here,&amp;quot; he said, from wherever he was.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have to run!” Chickpea yelled, hopping and pointing to the end of the alley with her one unbroken wing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was Diane. She inched toward them with one palm up and an empty potato sack in the other hand. “Wait!” she said. “I can get you to Springville. Just get in the sack, quick.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;11.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango picked up Chickpea and staggered to his feet. The energy to run had not arrived yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea drove her head into Pango’s chest trying to get him to start running. While doing this she yelled out to Diane, “I’ll just buy a ticket, no need to get in a sack.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My grandson can help you. He is very kind and has lots of money and many connections.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“‘What are you talking about? We can just buy tickets to Springville!”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diane pointed at the dead fox. “That’s a dead fox. You killed that fox right? You can’t buy a ticket.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Your crate has air holes, this isn’t improvisation. Pango, MOVE!”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango knew he had to put the memory down and stop looking at it. He could tell that staring at it from various angles in exasperation looking for a place to grip it, a way to contextualize it, and integrate it back into his understanding of the world with some consistency, might last forever. So he decided to set it down and look away in just a moment, but the moment kept growing longer and he had to remind himself of his intent to set the memory down many times.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My grandson said I might need it. He’s very smart like that, and kind, and has lots of —”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Pango, PLEASE MOVE!”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spear shafts pounded the stone around the corner, announcing a group of marching soldiers, in the direction opposite Diane. Pango and Chickpea would soon be cornered. Fear of the sound jolted Pango into focus, but too late for any decision making. The arithmetic at this point was simple, but uncomfortable. For murder, the party would kill them. This ferret only might kill them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;12.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Chickpea heard the noises, she gave up pushing her head into Pango’s chest and hung her head. “Ok, whatever. Do it.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they climbed into Diane’s potato sack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For hours they sat in Diane’s crate and said nothing. Pango used the silence to assess their situation and inspect his mind. It was obvious to him, undeniable, that he was an idiot. Not only had he repeated the mistake of his father, he had outdone it. By Pango’s hand, his mother was not only robbed of her son, but also her freedom. She would serve Pango’s own sentence because Chickpea was right, foxes cannot tell chickens apart. And he still couldn’t remember what the sentence for fraudsters was.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At dusk Pango held Chickpea so the bumps and jolts of Diane wheeling the crate to the dock did not hurt her broken wing. As he held Chickpea in this weakened state, he noticed an inconsistency in himself. Where he could easily see the fault within himself, a simple cause and effect between his crimes and his misfortune, he could not accuse his friend in the same way even when they shared the same crimes and misfortunes. Chickpea only wanted freedom from the party, and for this they shrank her world even further, taking her flight and confining her to the ground.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he considered his father, who faced the party without power, knowing that he had no power, and that they would take him away. He had always thought it was condemnable vanity to place the narrative of his life, his reputation for bravery, over his own family. But now Pango was in a crate facing exile or worse, and had gotten his own mother imprisoned, and he wondered if his own optimism was any more respectable than his father’s? Was Pango just as vain, or did his father also think something might have come from his efforts?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Chickpea, do you remember what the party’s punishment is for fraud?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She did not respond for a moment, and he could not see her face in the dark of the crate. Eventually she said “the cage. They put fraudsters in the cage.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least his mother and father would have one another.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango layed down to sleep as the crate was loaded onto a ship out of Northenden.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;3&#x2F;13.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Chapter 2: Plum</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://pangolune.com/2/</link>
            <guid>https://pangolune.com/2/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Plum Piquet was a loyal bear, and he thirsted for one of the white robes of the Beacons so that everyone else would know it too. When that morning Barry Metche confessed to looking at the illustrations in a book, Plum glared at him so that anyone who happened to look would see Plum’s indignant anger at such disrespect to The Academy. But Barry was a botanist, and when they dragged him out of the hall for his sin, the candidate pool shrunk by one. Plum appreciated that, privately.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;2&#x2F;1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beacon Gin was leading the appointment ceremony, which progressed from one tediously intricate traditional rite to the next at the pace of a lame tortoise, the kind of pace which, for those participating without an active role, made paying attention from beginning to end impossible, and lent a rare opportunity for one to get in touch with the more subtle recesses of their proprioception. It began in early morning with the ostensible purpose of naming five students who would embark into the realms, on the first of a career of missions which, if fruitful and honorable, would earn them the status of Beacon. Plum had probably daydreamed about this moment, if the duration of each daydream throughout his 18 years at The Academy were summed up, for longer than the ceremony itself would actually last, but his daydreams only featured the interesting moments, where the Beacon walked stoically through the rows and columns of students standing at attention, to approach and challenge the ones they deemed worthy of the long trials in the realms. These moments came every hour or so. Three of the chairs on stage for selected students had been filled. In the intervening time, Plum idled in his mind and became unwillingly aware of new itches, locales of problematic muscle tightness, a nonspecific sensation in his calves which may or may not be a product of circulatory activity (he did not know if veins and arteries were innervated), and the general complexity of maintaining upright posture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;2&#x2F;2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the headmaster announced that Beacon Gin would then select the botanist, the fourth of the five specialties eligible for the trials in the realms, the specialty to which Plum had devoted his entire life, Plum returned his attention to the ceremony. The adrenaline made him forget the weight of his shoulders and upper back. He fixed his at-attention posture, and resisted the (very strong) temptation to deviate from the expected forward stare to watch Beacon Gin as he wandered through the grid of students. Memories of his studies played in his mind&#x27;s eye, including some distant ones from his youth, in chronological sequence, composing a private and emotional picture autobiography of the plot of his life. This limited-scope narrative, which Plum constructed for the purposes of amplifying his anxiety over his imminent selection or non-selection as a botanist, began in the Blessed Garden, where Plum, at the tender age of three, became entranced by the quadriceps vines. Beacon Barley told him that if he looked closely, they had a pulse, just like his own quadriceps. When Plum saw it not only pulse but also flexed sometimes, Beacon Barley didn&#x27;t believe him, which little Plum made a stink about, loudly and indignantly pointing at the vine, which he could clearly see was pulsing and flexing, and reminding Beacon Barley that he just not two moments before explained quadriceps vines behave like his own quadriceps, and his own quadriceps flexed. Finally Plum got the old bear to put on some glasses and take a look, and then it was his turn to forfeit anything resembling a controlled manner. He rushed out of the garden and brought back with him four other Beacons, each of which looked at the vine, and then back at Plum, back-and-forth with this incredulous expression that drove little Plum into the fits of self-satisfied roll-on-the-floor laughter only available to a young child who has proved an elder wrong. More and more Beacons came, amazed, for reasons Plum still did not understand, that they could still observe the phenomenon in the vines with all of them in the room together. When their reaction matured out of the denial phase, they turned their attention to Plum, and praised him, showering him with more positive attention, affirmation, and validation that he would ever have thought to ask for. It was all for just seeing it, which still confused him, because Beacon Barley had been hanging out in the Blessed Garden babysitting little toddler bears for years, eagerly telling them to look at vines for their pulse, sometimes more than once, like a man armed with a new factoid on the lookout for anyone who might be impressed by their possession of the new factoid. Probabilistically someone else should have seen the vines flexing long ago, but these doubts only came in retrospect. At the time, all little Plum knew was that he ought to hang around the plants. People paid a lot of attention to him when he hung around plants and saw them doing things that other people apparently couldn&#x27;t see even though they were pretty obvious, and he liked the attention, so he kept hanging around plants. That&#x27;s how it all started, a lifelong devotion to looking at plants and seeing them do things. And now, Beacon Gin would tell him if all of it added up to enough.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plum, being a bear, had no skill for echolocation, but from his forward stare the only indication of Beacon Gin&#x27;s position was the echoing of his cane as it impacted the marble floor before each of his labored steps, so he tried anyway. It felt like they were getting louder, and in his mentally-constructed model of the rotunda&#x27;s great hall, Beacon Gin waddled toward him, resting on his twisted oakwood cane for a moment whenever he caught up with it, almost gratuitous in his slowness. The acoustics of the great hall complicated his modeling. Each impact echoed through the great hall, off the white brick walls around the rotunda, up the pillars rising from the floor, ascending until they hit the painted dome separating The Academy from Heaven, and sometimes he mixed up an echo with the real thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;2&#x2F;3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Plum,” Beacon Gin said softly, just behind him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providence. He was chosen. The next question was only a formality, as meaningless in the process as any one of the 18 steps it would take to reach the stage, or any of the muscle contractions his central nervous system would coordinate to lower himself into the fourth chair. The doubt in his mind over the past few moments had been performative, an accommodation for God, who, though She never seemed to leave the sacred chambers in which She lived above the painted dome, pulled most of the important strings at The Academy, and had opinions about unrepentant pride even if it was indulged only in thought. Plum&#x27;s place, he always at some level knew, was in the Beacon&#x27;s quarters at the top residential level of the rotunda. His true outfit was the white robe of the Beacons, social evidence that he was a signal of God&#x27;s light, a tool of strategic value in Her campaign to reunite the world which had been shattered into realms, to tear down the realm barriers which divine light could not cross. Plum did not feel entitled to this in a comparative way. It was not because he thought he was better or more deserving than other students. He felt it because the Beacons loved him his whole life, and he loved them too, and so how could they treat him any differently?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, Beacon Gin?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What season is it?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It always has been and always will be the third winter.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You will leave tomorrow morning and find a field sown with muscle vines. Watch them grow in one week. Take your place in the botanist’s chair.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;2&#x2F;4.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his dorm that night, Plum crawled into bed between clean sheets and the screams from the library did not disturb his peace. Often they did, because he worried he might be locked in the library screaming himself one day. But that night was his last night in The Academy as a green and naïve student. Tomorrow, he would venture into the realms God had created in the unified age, and realize Her will upon them. After his return his bedroom door would open to the balcony walkway around the circumference of the great hall. In the mornings he would look up and see the Founders on the painted dome, and from that height the screams from the library would be unable to reach him. With everything he had ever dreamed of, books would not tempt him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;2&#x2F;5.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Chapter 1: Pango</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://pangolune.com/1/</link>
            <guid>https://pangolune.com/1/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Pango pulled the peach out of the river and prepared to be disappointed by what he found inside. He discarded the fruit because he only cared about the pit. Holding it beside the gold ring he borrowed from his mother’s drawer, he measured its hue. It was useless. The pit of the peach was not made of gold, and he could not defeat the soldiers who held his father with an ordinary fruit seed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a future where Pango got his hands on an enchanted fruit and ate the golden seed inside—assuming eating it was how it worked—and on the other side of that act found a different world, a world without fear. Invulnerable, he would not quiver when a soldier raised his spear in threat. All powerful, he would casually retake Northenden from the party, scattering the mighty red vests into a mess of panic-stricken foxes who happened to be wearing matching outfits. He would liberate his father and Chickpea’s brother from the party prison, and everyone would revere him as a hero. All he had to do was find the path from the present to that future, instead of any of the other futures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present, a bad fall could break Pango’s bones and he wielded only the power of two chicken wings. He had a lot of ground to cover to become invulnerable and all powerful, which made disappointments in these early stages frustrating. If the peach he pulled out of the river had been enchanted and the pit was made of solid gold, Pango would have felt much better. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because he suggested the method and was not working alone, each failure, in addition to being frustrating, was also embarrassing. He and Chickpea made an unsparing offering to the river spirit of 70 ripe blueberries and 100 halves of termite before dipping this peach in the river water, but it came out unenchanted just like the ones they had dipped before. It took days to gather each offering, and because Chickpea neither believed in the river spirit nor enjoyed gathering berries and termites, each failed attempt cost Pango some of her patience and made him feel stupid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango lined all the pits up in a row, hoping at least to see some progression from not-gold to gold, some hint of progress. But the newest pit was no more gold than the last.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well?&amp;quot; Chickpea asked, too short to see over Pango’s wing, which he had carefully been holding in her line of sight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Good news Chickpea! This one is sort of reflective.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea nudged Pango aside to see for herself. &amp;quot;Which one is it?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;4.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango confessed it was the pit on the far right.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She turned it over in her hands. &amp;quot;Reflective means I see myself right? I’m a bird. I’m not seeing a bird.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;5.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It&#x27;s not much but it&#x27;s a little more than last time. I think we should try a bigger offering to the river spirit&amp;quot; Pango said. He didn’t think that, but he didn’t want her to say what he knew she was about to say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Pango this isn&#x27;t working. We need to go get the real golden peach pit.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pango agreed that the enchanted fruit was a nonnegotiable element of any valid plan. There was no hope of simply purchasing passage to Springville and setting up a new life beyond the reach of the party, not unless Chickpea could forget about her brother and Pango could forget about his father. Liberating the party prison was an essential step. But they had time. There was no need for rashness. His problem with the real golden peach pit was that trying to get it was absolutely crazy, unthinkable, and suicidal. It grew only in the garden at the top of Mount Ray, at the southern edge of the world. Mount Ray was too far away, too tall, and he thought the edge of the world was too strange a place to reasonably want to go. Attempting to persuade the river spirit to help was a longshot, he knew that much, but so was attempting to reach Mount Ray, and they had the river right there at home on the island of Northenden. He couldn’t become invincible if he died on an unnecessary hike.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;9.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Chickpea’s account her plan was simple and foolproof and obvious like getting out of bed. The idea came to her the week before, when they didn’t have Pango’s mother’s ring. He happened to have some gold paint, and they tested the gold-ness of each peach pit by dabbing the paint on it. It occurred to Chickpea to paint more than a dab, to paint the whole thing and make a fake golden peach core, and sell it to someone dumb for a lot of real gold. If they managed to sell just one, they could fund an expedition to Mount Ray. The traveling merchants and rich foxes from the south would make their annual trip to Northenden the next Sunday, and as the date approached Chickpea stopped suggesting and began insisting on her plan.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;7.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pointed out that where golden peach pits provided godlike powers and invincibility, fake golden peach pits provide only a few calories and grams of carbohydrates. What were these customers liable to do after they embarrassed or seriously injured themselves? Chickpea casually modified the plan to include only the sale of pits with a golden vein, marketed instead as an aphrodisiac, and considered the issue closed. But the obvious error and quickness with which this plan changed shape did not set Pango at ease.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;8.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his walk home he thought about Chickpea’s idea. She planned no further than getting the money to board a ship south to Springville. To the questions of how they would reach Mount Ray, how the pit actually worked, and how to overthrow the party with it, Chickpea said &amp;quot;We&#x27;re smart. We&#x27;ll figure it out.&amp;quot; That level of planning would not work for Pango.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chickpea insisted that Northenden was getting worse for birds by the day. She was possessed by a sense of urgency which instructed her to drag Pango beyond the city walls, through the lion lands, the haunted old marshes, and up Mount Ray, to the end of the world. To him it seemed wholly superior to acquire a golden peach pit here in Northenden and test it and understand it before placing any bets on it. She had never questioned his resolve out loud, but she never respected his prudence out loud either.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he neared his home he noticed even from a distance that it looked different. His thoughts became quiet as he squinted at the gradually closer picture. On the porch there was his mother, and that was an unusual place to find her, because she feared leaving the safety of home even to check the mail. On one hinge was the door, and that was usually on two hinges. Cracks and holes had been added to the windows.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Pango!&amp;quot; his mother screamed as she ran toward him and embraced him with both of her wings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;10.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She struggled to acknowledge his questions through her sobs and brief intrusions of panic. His legs could not move fast enough to keep up with her vigorously pushing him toward the house. When he stumbled she kept their pace by lifting him up and he had to kick his legs down in sync to free himself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they were both inside her breath slowed enough for him to catch key phrases and assemble them. Between urgent murmurings of &amp;quot;couldn&#x27;t find my little Pango&amp;quot;, she said &amp;quot;soldiers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;ransacked&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;fox bastards&amp;quot;. Soldiers had come and taken what they wanted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soldier&#x27;s cruelty had until then been an outside phenomenon, something that could not take place in his home any more than it could rain in a kitchen. Though it did not inspire him to literally leave the world by its southern edge, he felt his share of the world here had become smaller, and perhaps Chickpea was right that it would continue to shrink if they did not make progress.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he could never have the magic powers of the enchanted peach, Pango would at least like to have one of the red vests of the party members. Even the soldiers feared the foxes wearing a red vest with white trim. Their word was life and death, and they had no fear of soldiers while out or at home. Unlike his mother, they let their children wander outside, and could focus on whatever tasks they chose with a free mind until their children returned home at a time of the child’s choosing, not agreed upon beforehand. He wondered if they understood the value of their clothing, if they knew how much he would give for the same safety and freedom from fear. He knew they didn’t, but in frustration he still wondered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Pango,&amp;quot; she said as she contorted her face into a familiar expression of despair and gripped both of his shoulders, &amp;quot;they took the ring your father gave me.&amp;quot; Then her grip weakened and she covered her face with her wings again. &amp;quot;As if taking your father himself was not enough.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;11-12.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;No, I have the ring&amp;quot; he said without forethought and held it out for her to see.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her eyes fixated on it and she did not move. Pango realized he had made a mistake. He should have explained that he took it from the house, because the fear that was now overtaking her would leave no room for him to explain that he had not gone out in search of the soldiers, that he had not, upon finding them, risked death by stealing the ring back from them, or trying to start a fight, or accusing them of theft and attempting to negotiate, earning himself recognition and the further dangers that implied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One moment she was still. Then Pango was moved across the house by a rabid almost impersonal force and thrown into his room and he heard his mother propping a chair against the doorknob on the other side so that he could not escape.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;13-14.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ritual began. She would not let him out until her fear receded, which would take days. Through the garden window she would deliver meals three times a day and make light chitchat which he reluctantly indulged because he thought it calmed her and earned him an early release.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meals would come at precise times, never late or early by a minute. Breakfast came at 8 AM, lunch at 12 PM, dinner at 6 PM. His mother had spent more time looking at a clock than any other thing in life, and it was only within specific pre-negotiated slices of the clock that Pango experienced freedom. Returning at 5:02 PM when he had promised to return at 5 PM did not make Pango late. It made Pango dead. His mother preferred that he was not dead so he tried his best to stay alive. On her confident days she permitted him to venture all the way out to the river a few blocks west. He spent the other days locked in his room, a safe bubble for a fragile chicken in a dangerous world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where other children explored and memorized the terrain of Northenden, rushing through the forest playing soldier and freedom fighter, Pango spent his youth laying on the floor in his room and studying the terrain-like surface of the cracking ceiling paint overhead. A large mountain range split the terrain in half. Pango called it the Middle Mountain Range and it was created by rainwater leaking through the roof and weighing down the paint but not breaking it. In his world the force of water caused terrain to rise and erupt instead of erode. He imagined that outside somewhere there must be deep ravines carved out by running water, much deeper than the water running through them. He craved to walk through one so deep that the top could not be seen from the ground.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;15.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unpredictable anxieties in his mother made it impossible for him to predict which days he would have freedom to leave home. Without the ability to make or keep plans, there was no chance of making friends other than Chickpea. She spent her afternoons flying aimlessly above Northenden, and from her bird’s eye view she could see when Pango was at the river. Some afternoons when he wasn’t allowed to leave, he would go to the window and try to wave at Chickpea in the sky. He wanted to tell her he wouldn’t be able to make it and that she could stop waiting for him. But he knew she could not see through his window from her flying height.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;18.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he asked she would say she just liked to fly, but when Pango arrived at the river for the first time in many days the first thing he did was apologize until Chickpea made him stop. Except for Chickpea, Pango was alone. If all those blueberries and half termites could not sway the river spirit, it would probably never come around. Chickpea knew Pango had no more plans to try. If he didn’t help her she would run her scam and venture out alone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;19.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if he helped and they made money, he could buy books, and maybe learn another way to make a golden peach pit without leaving Northenden. Pango sat at his desk and set out the jar of gold paint, his brushes, the peach pits, and turned on his lamp. He began a long night of work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pangolune.com&#x2F;1&#x2F;20.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
